Charles E. Waring Papers 2008.0008
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Charles E. Waring Papers
undated, 1914-1988
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
2008.0008
3 Linear Feet
The collection contains correspondence to and from Charles E. Waring and Geraldine H. Waring. Dr. Waring was a professor in the Chemistry Department at the University of Connecticut from 1946 until his retirement in 1979.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by the estate of Geraldine Waring. Additional materials were transferred by the Chemistry Department in 2016.
Arrangement
The correspondence has been arranged chronologically and further subdivided between letters sent to Dr. Waring and those from him.
Series I: Correspondence (undated, 1914-1988, bulk 1933-1945)
Series II: Photographs and Ephemera (undated, circa 1944)
Biography
Charles E. Waring was born in Phildelphia, PA, in 1909 and attended Muskingum College for his undergraduate work (B.Sc., 1931). He then went to Ohio State University where he earned the Ph.D. in 1936. While at Ohio State, he met Geraldine Howald. On December 19, 1936, Waring with a bright new Ph.D. also acquired a wife, Geraldine. In 1936, Waring was hired as instructor of chemistry at the Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn. In 1939, he was one of five to be awarded the Lalor Foundation award for proficiency in chemical research. He chose to carry on his research at Oxford University, England, in collaboration with the internationally famous authority on chemical kinetics, Dr. C. N. Hinshelwood.
In the period 1936 to 1946, he rose from instructor to assistant professor at Brooklyn Poly. It was during this period that he initiated his research in the fields of kinetics and mechanism of gas and liquid phase reactions and free radical reactions; kinetics of fast reactions at ultra-high pressures; kinetics and thermodynamics of solid and liquid propellant systems; and combustion mechanisms of high energy fuels.
In 1946, Waring joined the faculty at the University of Connecticut as Head of the Chemistry Department. There were eight on the teaching staff in the department at the time. When he relinquished his administrative duties in 1966 to return to full time teaching, the department had grown to 22 members. Waring was able to carry on a full research program in addition to his administrative duties. During his tenure at the University, he served as adviser for 24 Ph.D. students and nine M.S. students. It was under Waring's leadership that the department was one of the leaders in the University to institute the Ph.D. program.
In addition to the academic research carried on in his research laboratories, Waring was very much involved in the application end of the science. From 1942 to 1946, he was a member of London Mission, OSRD. From 1946-1966, he was a Technical Aide, Division 16, NDRC. He spent the summers of 1951 to 1953 in Europe and England on a scientific and technical assignment for the U.S. Government. In 1961, while on leave from the University, he served as technical director and head of the Research Department, Naval Ordnance Test Station, China Lake. For his wartime service, he was awarded the Presidential Citation for Merit (WWII) for contributions in the field of physics, optics, and technical intelligence.
Charles Waring died on February 16, 1981.
[Biography researched by John Tanaka, Emeritus Professor of Chemistry, University of Connecticut, 2008.]
Scope and Contents
The collection consists primarily of correspondence between Geraldine Howald and Charles "Chic" Waring during their early courtship beginning in 1932 until their marriage in 1936. The letters from Chic to Gerry document their growing attachment, activities during college breaks, early employment experiences and wedding planning. Following their marriage in December 1936, the Mrs. Waring joined Dr. Waring in Brooklyn, NY, where he had moved several months prior after accepting a position at Polytechnic University in the Chemistry Department. The correspondence decreases substantially throughout the late 1930s and early 1940s with the exception of letters home to family while the Warings toured Europe. In February 1943, Charles Waring joined the Office of Scientific Research and Development in England. Although the correspondence to Mrs. Waring is expectedly vague on specifics, Dr. Waring wrote regularly and provided considerable information regarding his activities, travel and the individuals he met in the course of his work. Frequent mention is made of his travels around southern England (especially Chalgrove), Belgium, France and Germany between 1943 and his return to the United States in the summer of 1945.
The collection also includes letters, notes and postcards from friends and family, a few photographs of Dr. Waring in uniform, one image of his father and calling cards.
Educators; Photographs; Correspondence; Office of Scientific Research and Development; University of Connecticut; Waring, Charles E.; Waring, Geraldine H.
- Series I: Correspondence, undated, 1914-1988
  - Subseries A: Correspondence to Geraldine Howald Waring from Charles E. Waring, undated, 1932-1945; 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesA:GerrytoCharles
    - undated, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesA:CharlestoGerry/Box1:1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1932 June - August, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesA:CharlestoGerry/Box1:2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1932 September - December, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesA:CharlestoGerry/Box1:3 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1933 February, June - July, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesA:CharlestoGerry/Box1:4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1933 August - September, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesA:CharlestoGerry/Box1:5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1934 June - July, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesA:CharlestoGerry/Box1:6 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1934 August - December, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesA:CharlestoGerry/Box1:7 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1935 March, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesA:CharlestoGerry/Box1:8 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1936 September, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesA:CharlestoGerry/Box1:9 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1936 October, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesA:CharlestoGerry/Box1:10 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1936 November, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesA:CharlestoGerry/Box2:11 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 1936 December, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesA:CharlestoGerry/Box2:12 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 1939 July, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesA:CharlestoGerry/Box2:13 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 1941 April, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesA:CharlestoGerry/Box2:14 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - 1943 December, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesA:CharlestoGerry/Box2:15 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 1943 February, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesA:CharlestoGerry/Box2:16 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 1943 March - December, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesA:CharlestoGerry/Box2:17 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 1944 April - July, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesA:CharlestoGerry/Box2:18 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - 1944 July - September, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesA:CharlestoGerry/Box2:19 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - 1944 October - December, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesA:CharlestoGerry/Box2:20 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - 1945 February - May, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesA:CharlestoGerry/Box2:21 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - 1945 August, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesA:CharlestoGerry/Box3:22 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Subseries B: Correspondence to Charles E. Waring from Geraldine Howald Waring, undated, 1944-1945; 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesB:GerrytoCharles
    - 1944 July - August, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesB:GerrytoCharles/Box3:23 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - 1944 September, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesB:GerrytoCharles/Box3:24 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - 1944 October, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesB:GerrytoCharles/Box3:25 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - 1945 August, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesB:GerrytoCharles/Box3:26 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Subseries C: Correspondence to and from Warings and others, undated, 1914-1988; 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesC:Others
    - undated, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesC:Others/Box3:27 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - 1914, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesC:Others/Box3:28 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - 1932, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesC:Others/Box3:29 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - 1939, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesC:Others/Box3:30 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - 1940, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesC:Others/Box3:31 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - 1943, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesC:Others/Box3:32 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - 1944, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesC:Others/Box3:33 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - 1951-1952, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesC:Others/Box3:34 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - 1973, 1974, 1979, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesC:Others/Box3:35 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - 1986-1988, 2008-0008/SeriesI:Correspondence/SubseriesC:Others/Box3:36 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Series II: Photographs and Ephmera, undated, circa 1944
  - Calling cards for Charles E. Waring, undated; 2008-0008/SeriesII:PhotosEphemera/Box3:38 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Charles E. Waring's family (father, mother and possibly sister Wilma, 3 B & W mounted prints), undated; 2008-0008/SeriesII:PhotosEphemera/Box3:40 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Dr. Waring in uniform (3 B & W snapshots ), 1944; 2008-0008/SeriesII:PhotosEphemera/Box3:37 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Medal for Gerry Waring's volunteer work, undated; 2008-0008/SeriesII:PhotosEphemera/Box3:39 (Box 3, Folder 39)